Otto Fleischmann Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Otto Fleischmann Papers 1910-1985 (bulk 1936-1960)
MSS85406
Fleischmann, Otto, 1896-1963
1,000 items
3 containers
1 linear foot
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst. Correspondence, photographs, writings, and printed matter relating to Fleischmann's experiences as a Viennese psychoanalyst and associate of Raoul Wallenberg in Budapest during German Nazi occupation.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Aichhorn, August, 1878-1949.; Fleischmann, Otto, 1896-1963.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982.; Schlick, Moritz, 1882-1936.; Szalai, P치l, 1915-1994.; Wallenberg, Raoul, 1912-1947.
Subjects
Jews--Hungary.; Psychoanalysis--Austria--Vienna.; World War, 1939-1945--Hungary.
Places
Hungary--History--1918-1945.
Occupations
Psychoanalysts.
Provenance
The papers of Otto Fleischmann, psychoanalyst, were given to the Library of Congress by Esther M. Fleischmann in 2008.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Otto Fleischmann are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Otto Fleischmann was born January 24,1896, in M칩r, Hungary. Although originally a juris doctor, he studied philosophy with Moritz Schlick at the University of Vienna and in 1938 became a Freudian pschoanalyst under the mentorship of August Aichhorn. Fleischmann was associated with many psychoanalysts including Anna Freud. After the German Nazi takeover of Austria, Fleischmann went to Budapest, Hungary. In 1944, with the German occupation of Hungary, he received protection from the Swedish Foreign Ministry through diplomatic cover provided by Raoul Wallenberg. Fleischmann subsequently worked with Wallenberg in his efforts to save Jews in Hungary, 1944-1945. In 1948, he returned to Vienna from Budapest to help Aichhorn revive the Vienna Psychoanalytic Society (WPV) which had been repressed under Nazi rule. He served as Secretary and Vice President of the WPV until his emigration to the United States to join the faculty of the Menninger Clinic in Topeka, Kansas, in 1949. He died January 8, 1963, in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Otto Fleischmann (1896-1963) span the years 1910-1985, with the bulk of the material dating from 1936 to 1960. The papers are in English, German, Hungarian, Russian, and Swedish and are organized alphabetically by subject matter and type of material.
Fleischmann had a long friendly relationship with Anna Freud, and the papers include many letters from her as well as writings, both published and unpublished. She also is represented in a file of photographs. Many photographs are from conferences, but one folder contains informal snapshots of Fleischmann, Freud, and August Aichhorn while in Lausanne, Switzerland, in 1948.
Also of special interest are the papers from Fleischmann's time in Budapest, Hungary, during World War II. Included are documents provided by Raoul Wallenberg at the Swedish Foreign Ministry to Fleischmann that protected him from German Nazi authorities in 1944, including a photostatic copy of his "Schutz-Pass." There are photographs of Fleischmann and Wallenberg and documents and lists from Fleischmann's work with Wallenberg. Also in the papers are documents written by Fleischmann to Soviet and Hungarian authorities after the disappearance of Wallenberg in January of 1945. Other documents refer to P치l Szalai, the high-ranking member of the Budapest police force who helped Wallenberg in his efforts to save the Jews of Budapest.
The papers include a multivolume handwritten manuscript by the German philosopher Moritz Schlick (1882-1936). The title varies from volume to volume, but the first volume's title is "Natur, Kultur, Kunst." Schlick was one of the first to make the work of physicist Albert Einstein popularly understood.
Material relating to Sigmund Freud consists primarily of funeral orations, a medical case history, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous material. However, there is one folder of photostatic copies of documents written by Freud.
Material from Fleischmann's time spent in the United States concerns his book and journal collections and a 1959 American Psychoanalytic Association panel on male homosexuality.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject matter and type of material.
Container List
- Aichorn, August, 1947-1949, undated (Box 1)
- American Psychoanalytic Association panel on overt male homosexuality (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1959, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Bibliographies, 1960, undated (Box 1)
- Book and journal purchases, 1951-1960 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1938-1949, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
- Freud, Anna (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1957 (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
    - Published, 1944-1954 (Box 1)
    - Unpublished, 1946-1948, 1966, undated (Box 1)
- Freud, Sigmund (Box 1)
  - Funeral orations by Ernest Jones and Stefan Zweig, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Medical case history by Max Schur, 1952-1956, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1947-1960 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1922-1948, 1956, undated (Box 2)
  - Photostatic copies of documents, 1910, 1918-1936 (Box 2)
- Personal library, 1958-1963 (Box 2)
- Photographs (Box 2)
  - Conferences and meetings, 1947-1951, 1962, undated (Box 2)
  - Lausanne, Switzerland, with August Aichorn and Anna Freud, 1948 (Box 2)
- Printed matter, 1913-1962, undated (Box 2)
- Schlick, Moritz, "Natur, Kultur, Kunst," manuscript, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
- Wallenberg, Raoul (Box 3)
  - After Soviet arrest and concerning P치l Szalai, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - Miscellany, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - News clippings, 1947, 1957, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1944 (Box 3)
  - "Schutz-pass" and other Swedish foreign ministry protective papers for Fleischmann, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Tamm, Alfhild, and psychoanalytic societies in Hungary and Sweden, 1944-1945 (Box 3)